<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
]>

<chapter id="references">
	<title>References</title>
	<remark>display links to other useful, more advanced systemtap docs - http://sourceware.org/systemtap/documentation.html, http://sourceware.org/systemtap/wiki/HomePage</remark>
	
<para>
	This chapter enumerates other references for more information about SystemTap. It is advisable 
	that you refer to these sources in the course of writing advanced probes and tapsets.
</para>

<variablelist>

<varlistentry>
	<term>SystemTap Wiki</term>
<listitem>
<para>
	The <citetitle>SystemTap Wiki</citetitle> is a collection of links and articles related to the 
	deployment, usage, and development of SystemTap. You can find it in 
	<ulink url=" http://sourceware.org/systemtap/wiki/HomePage"/>.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>	
	
<varlistentry>
	<term>SystemTap Tutorial</term>
<listitem>
<para>
	Much of the content in this book comes from the <citetitle>SystemTap Tutorial</citetitle>.
	The <citetitle>SystemTap Tutorial</citetitle> is a more appropriate reference for 
	users with intermediate to advanced knowledge of C++ and kernel development, and can be found at 
	<ulink url="http://sourceware.org/systemtap/tutorial/"/>.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
	<term>man stapprobes</term>
<listitem>
<para>
The <filename>stapprobes</filename> man page enumerates a variety of probe points supported by SystemTap, along with additional aliases 
defined by the SystemTap tapset library. The bottom of the man page includes a list of other man pages 
enumerating similar probe points for specific system components, such as
	  <filename>stapprobes.scsi</filename>, <filename>stapprobes.kprocess</filename>, 
<filename>stapprobes.signal</filename>, etc.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>	

<varlistentry>
	<term>man stapfuncs</term>
<listitem>
<para>
	The <filename>stapfuncs</filename> man page enumerates numerous functions supported by the SystemTap tapset 
	library,  along with the prescribed syntax for each one. Note, however, that this is not a
	complete list of <emphasis>all</emphasis> supported functions; there are more undocumented 
	functions available. 	
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
	<term>SystemTap Language Reference</term>
<listitem>
<para>
	This document is a comprehensive reference of SystemTap's language constructs and syntax. It is
	recommended for users with a rudimentary to intermediate knowledge of C++ and other similar 
	programming languages. The <citetitle>SystemTap Language Reference</citetitle> is available to all 
	users at <ulink url="http://sourceware.org/systemtap/langref/"/> 
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
	<term>Tapset Developers Guide</term>
<listitem>
<para>
	Once you have sufficient proficiency in writing SystemTap scripts, you can then try your hand out 
	on writing your own tapsets. The <citetitle>Tapset Developers Guide</citetitle> describes how to 
	add functions to your tapset library.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
	<term>Test Suite</term>
<listitem>
<para>
	The <filename>systemtap-testsuite</filename> package allows you to test the entire SystemTap
	toolchain without having to build from source. In addition, it also contains numerous examples of 
	SystemTap scripts you can study and test; some of these scripts are also documented in 
	<xref linkend="useful-systemtap-scripts"/>.
</para>

<para>
	By default, the example scripts included in <filename>systemtap-testsuite</filename> are located 
	in <filename>/usr/share/systemtap/testsuite/systemtap.examples</filename>.
</para>	
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<!--	
<varlistentry>
	<term></term>
<listitem>
<para>
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
-->
</variablelist>
	
	
</chapter>

