<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
]>

<chapter id="understanding-how-systemtap-works">
  <title>Understanding How SystemTap Works</title>
  <remark>
    Short summary; probes, handlers, events
  </remark>

  <para>
    SystemTap allows users to write and reuse simple scripts to deeply
    examine the activities of a running Linux system. These scripts can be
    designed to extract data, filter it, and summarize it quickly (and
    safely), enabling the diagnosis of complex performance (or even
    functional) problems.
  </para>

  <para>The essential idea behind a SystemTap script is to name
    <emphasis>events</emphasis>, and to give them
    <emphasis>handlers</emphasis>. When SystemTap runs the script, SystemTap
    monitors for the event; once the event occurs, the Linux kernel then runs
    the handler as a quick sub-routine, then resumes.
  </para>

  <para>
    There are several kind of events; entering/exiting a function, timer
    expiration, session termination, etc. A handler is a series of script
    language statements that specify the work to be done whenever the event
    occurs. This work normally includes extracting data from the event context,
    storing them into internal variables, or printing results.
</para>

  <section id="understanding-architecture-tools">
    <title>Architecture</title>
    <remark>
      ** add diagram, describe architecture, enumerate common tools
    </remark>

    <remark>
      ** architecture diagram must be simpler, if at all included
    </remark>

    <remark>
      ** add design advantages? e.g. "building kmods on-the-fly allows safer
      execution of script etc etc"
    </remark>

    <para>
      A SystemTap session begins when you run a SystemTap script. This
      session occurs in the following fashion:
    </para>

    <procedure id="systemtapsession">
      <title>SystemTap Session</title>

      <step>
	<para>
	  First, SystemTap checks the script against the existing tapset library
	  (normally in <filename>/usr/share/systemtap/tapset/</filename> for any
	  tapsets used.
	</para>
      </step>

      <step>
	<para>SystemTap then translates the script to C, running the system C
	  compiler to create a kernel module from it. The tools that perform
	  this step are contained in the <filename>systemtap</filename> package
	  (refer to <xref linkend="installproper"/> for more information).
	</para>
      </step>

      <step>
	<para>
	  SystemTap loads the module, then enables all the probes (events and
	  handlers) in the script. The <command>staprun</command> in the
	  <filename>systemtap-runtime</filename> package (refer to <xref
	  linkend="installproper"/> for more information) provides this
	  functionality.
	</para>
      </step>

<!--	<step><para>SystemTap loads the module, then enables all the probed events by "hooking" those events into the kernel.</para></step>
		-->
      <step>
	<para>
	  As the events occur, their corresponding handlers are executed.
	</para>
      </step>

      <step>
	<para>
	  Once the SystemTap session is terminated, the probes are disabled, and
	  the kernel module is unloaded.
	</para>
      </step>
	<!--
	<step><para>Once the SystemTap session is terminated, the hooked events are disconnected from the kernel; afterwards, the kernel module is unloaded.</para></step>-->    
    </procedure>

    <para>This sequence is driven from a single command-line program:
    <command>stap</command>. This program is SystemTap's main front-end
    tool. For more information about <command>stap</command>, refer to
    <command>man stap</command> (once SystemTap is properly installed on your
    machine).
    </para>

  </section>
<xi:include href="Scripts.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
<xi:include href="ScriptConstructs.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
<xi:include href="Arrays.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
<!--	
	<section id="understanding-scripts">
		<title>SystemTap Scripts</title>
		
		<remark>
			** definition, significance, structure, very basic examples, reference to later chapter (how to read library of preset SystemTap scripts in this book, using them)
		</remark>
	</section>
	-->
  <section id="understanding-tapsets">
    <title>Tapsets</title>

    <remark>
      definition, significance, difference with stap scripts (previous section),
      library of tapsets in system: location
    </remark>
		
    <para>
      <firstterm>Tapsets</firstterm> are scripts that form a library of
      pre-written probes and functions to be used in SystemTap scripts. When a
      user runs a SystemTap script, SystemTap checks the script's probe events
      and handlers against the tapset library; SystemTap then loads the
      corresponding probes and functions before translating the script to C
      (refer to <xref linkend="understanding-architecture-tools"/> for
      information on what transpires in a SystemTap session).
    </para>
<!--		
		<para>
			Simply put, the tapset library is an abstraction layer designed to make it easier for users to define events and functions. In a way, tapsets provide useful "aliases" for functions that users may want to specify as an event; knowing the proper alias to use is, for the most part, easier than understanding how to specify a specific kernel function.
		</para>	
		-->
    <para>
      Like SystemTap scripts, tapsets use the filename extension
      <filename>.stp</filename>. The standard library of tapsets is located in
      <filename>/usr/share/systemtap/tapset/</filename> by default. However,
      unlike SystemTap scripts, tapsets are not meant for direct execution;
      rather, they constitute the library from which other scripts can pull
      definitions.
    </para>	

    <para>
      Simply put, the tapset library is an abstraction layer designed to make it
      easier for users to define events and functions. In a manner of speaking,
      tapsets provide useful aliases for functions that users may want to
      specify as an event; knowing the proper alias to use is, for the most
      part, easier than remembering specific kernel functions that might vary
      between kernel versions.
    </para>	

<!-- 			understanding how to specify a specific kernel function. -->
				
    <para>
      Several handlers and functions in <xref linkend="systemtapscript-events"/>
      and <xref linkend="systemtapscript-functions"/> are defined in tapsets.
      For example, <command>thread_indent()</command> is defined in
      <filename>indent.stp</filename>.
    </para>

    <remark>
      any other details to be included? i dont want to dwell too long here,
      though, since IMHO tapset development is beyond the scope of this
      "beginner's guide"
    </remark>

  </section>

</chapter>
